<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mauro Maver</title>
<link>https://www.mauromaver.eu/omnia.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.mauromaver.eu/omnia.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Portfolio</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.52</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Repressive role of GLK in vindoline and TIA pathway regulation in Catharanthus roseus</title>
  <dc:creator>Mauro Maver</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_IX/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="drop-cap">
<p>The plant <em>Catharanthus roseus</em> is of significant scientific interest because it is the primary and only source for the biosynthesis of the two terpenoid indole alkaloids (TIAs), vinblastine and vincristine, which are widely used in chemotherapy treatments. A distinctive feature of TIAs and the vindoline pathway (one of the downstream TIA pathways) is their strong accumulation in developing leaves, followed by their decrease as the leaf matures<span class="citation" data-cites="mall2019influence"><sup>1</sup></span>. However, despite the biosynthetic pathway being extensively characterised<span class="citation" data-cites="mizukami1979purification"><sup>2</sup></span>, the exact regulatory mechanisms underlying this developmental pattern remain largely unexplored.</p>
</div>
<p>Recently<span class="citation" data-cites="liu2019gata"><sup>3</sup></span>, two transcription factors (TF) involved in regulating the vindoline pathway have been identified: CrPIF1, acting as a repressor in dark conditions and CrGATA1, acting as an activator in the presence of light. Alongside GATAs, GOLDEN2-LIKE (GLK) is a TF known in plants for its key role in chloroplast biogenesis in young shoots and developing leaves. In fact, when etiolated shoots are exposed to light, GLK activates genes for chlorophyll biosynthesis and chloroplast maturation. However, its expression is inhibited in mature leaves.</p>
<p>In this context, <em>Cole-Osborn et al.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="cole2024role"><sup>4</sup></span> investigated the potential role of the transcription factor GLK in the developmental activation of TIA biosynthesis, particularly vindoline biosynthesis, based on the similarity in leaf-level regulation between GLK and the vindoline pathway.</p>
<p>The authors identified a single GLK homolog in <em>C.roseus</em>. Although many plants possess two GLK proteins, previous studies have shown that all C<sub>4</sub> plants and only some C<sub>3</sub> plants have two GLKs. <em>C.roseus</em> is a C<sub>3</sub> plant, and these results are thus consistent with the literature<span class="citation" data-cites="wang2013evolution"><sup>5</sup></span>. Additionally, multiple GLK binding motifs were identified in many vindoline pathway promoters, supporting the hypothesis that CrGLK could indeed modulate their expression.</p>
<p>However, although GLK was initially hypothesised to act as an activator, experiments demonstrated quite the opposite. In the first experiment, the expression of <em>CrGLK</em>, the vindoline pathway, and some TIA genes were monitored in leaves at different developmental stages (immature and mature leaves) and light intensities (low and moderate light). In general, vindoline/TIA pathway genes were more highly expressed in immature leaves and moderate light. On the other hand, <em>CrGLK</em> was more highly expressed in mature and low light conditions. This negative correlation, although preliminary, would support the hypothesis of CrGLK as a non-activator of the vindoline pathway.</p>
<p>To functionally characterise CrGLK, the authors used the virus-induced gene silencing (VIGS) technique to silence <em>CrGLK</em>, applying the same conditions as the previous experiment. As a positive control for the successful silencing of <em>CrGLK</em>, the expression of <em>CrLHCB2.2</em>, known to be strongly activated by GLKs<span class="citation" data-cites="waters2009glk"><sup>6</sup></span>, was monitored. The <em>CrGLK</em>-silenced plants exhibited a clear phenotype, with pale green leaves and lower chlorophyll <em>a</em> and chlorophyll <em>b</em> contents. This phenotype is consistent with that shown by double mutants <em>glk1</em> <em>glk2</em> in <em>Arabidopsis thaliana</em>, reconfirming the presence of a single copy of GLK in <em>C.roseus</em> and its positive correlation with chlorophyll accumulation. Furthermore, the silencing of <em>CrGLK</em> led to increased expression of vindoline and TIA pathway genes (except for the <em>D4H</em> gene); this effect was particularly evident under moderate light conditions and in immature leaves, under which <em>GLK</em> expression is normally high.</p>
<p>Similarly to the VIGS silencing, the authors studied the effects of two chemicals, Norflurazon (Nor) and Lincomycin (Lin), capable of inducing chloroplast retrograde signalling, strongly repressing <em>GLK</em> and <em>LHCB2.2</em>, and disrupting chloroplast development. From this experiment, it was observed that treatment with Lin induced repression of <em>CrGLK</em>, <em>CrLHCB2.2</em>, and <em>D4H</em> while strongly inducing vindoline/TIA pathway genes. These results and those obtained with VIGS suggest that CrGLK does not activate but instead may repress TIA biosynthesis. Interestingly, Nor did not have the same effects as Lin, indicating that simply reducing <em>CrGLK</em> is not sufficient, and other mechanisms may be involved.</p>
<p>In conclusion, <em>Cole-Osborn et al.</em> identified and functionally characterised the single GLK homolog in <em>C.roseus</em> and observed its negative correlation with regulating vindoline and TIA pathway expression genes. These findings suggest a repressive rather than an activating role for CrGLK, providing new insights into the regulation of this important metabolic pathway.</p>
<hr>
<div style="text-align: center">
<iframe width="600" height="450" src="Omnia_focus_IX.pdf">
</iframe>
</div>
<div class="PDF">
<p>👉 <a href="Omnia_focus_IX.pdf" title="Here you can download the PDF version">Click here for the PDF</a> 👈</p>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p><strong>Original article</strong></p>
<p>Cole‐Osborn L.F., McCallan S.A., Prifti O., Abu R., Sjoelund V. &amp; Lee‐Parsons C.W.T. (2024). The role of the Golden2‐like (GLK) transcription factor in regulating terpenoid indole alkaloid biosynthesis in Catharanthus roseus. <em>Plant Cell Reports</em>, <strong>43</strong>: 141. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00299-024-03208-9">doi.org/10.1007/s00299-024-03208-9</a></p>
<p><strong>List of abbreviations</strong></p>
<p><strong>TIA</strong>, terpenoid indole alkaloid <strong>•</strong> <strong>PIF1</strong>, phytochrome-interacting factor 1 <strong>•</strong> <strong>GATA1</strong>, GATA-binding factor 1 <strong>•</strong> <strong>GLK</strong>, golden2-like <strong>•</strong> <strong>VIGS</strong>, virus-induced gene silencing <strong>•</strong> <strong>LHCB2.2</strong>, light harvesting complex subunit B2.2 <strong>•</strong> <strong>D4H</strong>, desacetoxyvindoline 4-hydroxylase.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>




<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-mall2019influence" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Mall, M. <em>et al.</em> Influence of seasonal and ontogenic parameters on the pattern of key terpenoid indole alkaloids biosynthesized in the leaves of catharanthus roseus. <em>South African Journal of Botany</em> <strong>123</strong>, 98–104 (2019).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-mizukami1979purification" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Mizukami, H., Nordlov, H., Lee, S.-L. &amp; Scott, A. I. Purification and properties of strictosidine synthetase (an enzyme condensing tryptamine and secologanin) from catharanthus roseus cultured cells. <em>Biochemistry</em> <strong>18</strong>, 3760–3763 (1979).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-liu2019gata" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Liu, Y., Patra, B., Pattanaik, S., Wang, Y. &amp; Yuan, L. GATA and phytochrome interacting factor transcription factors regulate light-induced vindoline biosynthesis in catharanthus roseus. <em>Plant Physiology</em> <strong>180</strong>, 1336–1350 (2019).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-cole2024role" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Cole-Osborn, L. F. <em>et al.</em> The role of the Golden2-like (GLK) transcription factor in regulating terpenoid indole alkaloid biosynthesis in catharanthus roseus. <em>Plant Cell Reports</em> <strong>43</strong>, 141 (2024).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-wang2013evolution" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">5. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Wang, P. <em>et al.</em> Evolution of GOLDEN2-LIKE gene function in c 3 and c 4 plants. <em>Planta</em> <strong>237</strong>, 481–495 (2013).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-waters2009glk" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">6. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Waters, M. T. <em>et al.</em> GLK transcription factors coordinate expression of the photosynthetic apparatus in arabidopsis. <em>The Plant Cell</em> <strong>21</strong>, 1109–1128 (2009).</div>
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>© 2024 Mauro Maver | This work is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{maver2024,
  author = {Maver, Mauro},
  publisher = {Omnia},
  title = {Repressive Role of {GLK} in Vindoline and {TIA} Pathway
    Regulation in {Catharanthus} Roseus},
  volume = {1},
  number = {9},
  date = {2024-07-02},
  url = {https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_IX/},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.12608361},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {The study by *Cole-Osborn et al.* explores the regulatory
    role of the transcription factor GLK in the biosynthesis of
    terpenoid indole alkaloids (TIAs) in *Catharanthus roseus*,
    revealing that CrGLK acts as a repressor rather than an activator of
    the vindoline pathway. These findings provide new insights into the
    developmental regulation of TIA biosynthesis, which is crucial for
    chemotherapy treatments.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-maver2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<div class="">Maver, M. Repressive role of GLK in vindoline
and TIA pathway regulation in Catharanthus roseus. <em>Omnia Focus</em>
vol. 1 Preprint at <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12608361">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12608361</a>
(2024).</div>
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_IX/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_IX/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>TWA1: a novel thermosensor enhancing plant thermotolerance</title>
  <dc:creator>Mauro Maver</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VIII/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="drop-cap">
<p>In the plant kingdom, each species has an optimal temperature range for growth and development. However, sudden climatic fluctuations or prolonged periods of intense heat can severely challenge their survival. When temperatures exceed this range, plants activate heat-stress responses (HSR) to adapt to these stressful conditions. These adaptation and response strategies involve various developmental processes in the plant<span class="citation" data-cites="casal2019thermomorphogenesis"><sup>1</sup></span>. Heat triggers the HSR through heat-shock factor 1 (HSF1) transcription factors, which induce the expression of heat-shock proteins (HSPs), helping the plant adapt to heat. Additionally, the HSR involves several phytohormone pathways, with abscisic acid (ABA) playing a crucial role in regulating the plant’s water status, promoting thermotolerance, and enhancing plant acclimation<span class="citation" data-cites="cutler2010abscisic yoshida2019revisiting"><sup>2,3</sup></span>.</p>
</div>
<p>To better understand the mechanisms of temperature perception and the induction of thermotolerance, <em>Bohn et al.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="bohn2024temperature"><sup>4</sup></span> examined different lines of <em>Arabidopsis thaliana</em> that were hyper-responsive or insensitive to ABA under heat stress. Among all the mutants tested, one showed strong thermosensitivity, and the gene locus was subsequently named <em>THERMO-WITH-ABA-RESPONSE 1</em> (<em>TWA1</em>). Expressed throughout the plant, it encodes a predicted intrinsically disordered protein of 130 kDa with two potential ethylene-responsive-element-binding-factor-associated amphiphilic repression (EAR) motifs (LxLxL).</p>
<p>In a yeast two-hybrid (Y2H) system, TWA1 was found to interact with JASMONATE-ASSOCIATED MYC-LIKE 2 (JAM2), a transcription factor involved in jasmonate (JA) hormone signalling<span class="citation" data-cites="sasaki2013basic song2013bhlh"><sup>5,6</sup></span>, and with the co-repressors TOPLESS (TPL) and TOPLESS-RELATED (TPR), forming a repressor complex. However, this interaction is highly temperature-dependent. Specifically, TWA1 only accumulates in nuclear subdomains at elevated temperatures (30-35°C), and its conformational changes allow physical interaction with JAM2 and TPL/TPR. These temperature-dependent structural rearrangements are mediated by a 20 amino acid sequence in the amino-terminal region of TWA1, defined as the Highly Variable Region (HVR). The HVR thus confers strong thermosensitivity to TWA1.</p>
<p>Homologues of TWA1 have been identified in both monocotyledons and dicotyledons. An interesting aspect is the role of HVR in thermal sensing, particularly its amino acid sequence. Although they have comparable inhibitory effects at 30-35°C, their thermal sensitivity or temperature threshold varies. For instance, half-maximum inhibitory values (IT<sub>50</sub>) of 20°C, 26°C, and 30°C were observed for TWA1 in <em>A.lyrata</em> (cold acclimated), <em>A.thaliana</em>, and <em>Sinapis alba</em> (Mediterranean climate), respectively. Similarly, this threshold has been shown to affect accumulation and interaction with JAM2 and TPL and, consequently, the activation of its inhibitor effects.</p>
<p>Moreover, tests involving the overexpression of TWA1 (TWA1(oe)) have demonstrated its ability to confer an enhanced thermotolerance, both basal and acquired, without impacting growth and photosynthesis. No significant differences in growth, photosynthesis, and gas exchange were observed between WT and TWA1(oe) when grown at 20°C. These findings reconfirm the activation of TWA1 only above specific temperatures. Additionally, the improved thermotolerance of TWA1 is not due to the constitutive upregulation of HSP transcripts.</p>
<p>TWA1 presents an interesting parallel with other known thermal sensors, such as EARLY FLOWERING 3 (ELF3) in <em>A.thaliana</em><span class="citation" data-cites="jung2020prion"><sup>7</sup></span>. However, thermally, TWA1 acts oppositely to ELF3, repressing gene expression at high temperatures and being much more sensitive to temperature changes.</p>
<p>In conclusion, <em>Bohn et al.</em> have identified a new thermosensor, TWA1, and demonstrated its requirement for thermotolerance and the transcriptional upregulation of HSFA2 and HSPs in <em>A.thaliana</em>. The potential of TWA1 in breeding and biotechnology is vast, providing valuable tools for enhancing crop acclimation to the growing issue of global warming. Additionally, TWA1 and its orthologues represent a valuable resource in the emerging field of thermogenetics<span class="citation" data-cites="chee2022thermogenetics"><sup>8</sup></span>.</p>
<hr>
<div style="text-align: center">
<iframe width="600" height="450" src="Omnia_focus_VIII.pdf">
</iframe>
</div>
<div class="PDF">
<p>👉 <a href="Omnia_focus_VIII.pdf" title="Here you can download the PDF version">Click here for the PDF</a> 👈</p>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p><strong>Original article</strong></p>
<p>Bohn L., Huang J., Weidig S., Yang Z., Heidersberger C., Genty B., Falter-Braun P., Christmann A. &amp; Grill E. (2024). The temperature sensor TWA1 is required for thermotolerance in Arabidopsis. <em>Nature</em>, <strong>629</strong>: 1126–1132. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-024-07424-x">doi.org/10.1038/s41586-024-07424-x</a></p>
<p><strong>List of abbreviations</strong></p>
<p><strong>HSR</strong>, heat-stress responses <strong>•</strong> <strong>HSPs</strong>, heat-shock proteins <strong>•</strong> <strong>ABA</strong>, abscisic acid <strong>•</strong> <strong><em>TWA1</em></strong>, <em>THERMO-WITH-ABA-RESPONSE 1</em> <strong>•</strong> <strong>Da</strong>, Dalton <strong>•</strong> <strong>EAR</strong>, ethylene-responsive-element-binding-factor-associated amphiphilic repression <strong>•</strong> <strong>Y2H</strong>, yeast-to-hybrid <strong>•</strong> <strong>JAM2</strong>, JASMONATE- ASSOCIATED MYC2-LIKE 2 <strong>•</strong> <strong><em>TPL</em></strong>, <em>TOPLESS</em> <strong>•</strong> <strong><em>TPR</em></strong>, <em>TOPLESS-RELATED</em> <strong>•</strong> <strong>HVR</strong>, highly variable region <strong>•</strong> <strong>TWA1(oe)</strong>, <em>TWA1</em>-overexpressed <strong>•</strong> <strong><em>ELF3</em></strong>, <em>EARLY FLOWERING 3</em> <strong>•</strong> <strong>HSFA2</strong>, heat-shock transcription factor A2.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>




<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-casal2019thermomorphogenesis" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Casal, J. J. &amp; Balasubramanian, S. Thermomorphogenesis. <em>Annual review of plant biology</em> <strong>70</strong>, 321–346 (2019).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-cutler2010abscisic" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Cutler, S. R., Rodriguez, P. L., Finkelstein, R. R. &amp; Abrams, S. R. Abscisic acid: Emergence of a core signaling network. <em>Annual review of plant biology</em> <strong>61</strong>, 651–679 (2010).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-yoshida2019revisiting" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Yoshida, T., Christmann, A., Yamaguchi-Shinozaki, K., Grill, E. &amp; Fernie, A. R. Revisiting the basal role of ABA–roles outside of stress. <em>Trends in Plant Science</em> <strong>24</strong>, 625–635 (2019).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-bohn2024temperature" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Bohn, L. <em>et al.</em> The temperature sensor TWA1 is required for thermotolerance in arabidopsis. <em>Nature</em> 1–7 (2024).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-sasaki2013basic" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">5. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Sasaki-Sekimoto, Y. <em>et al.</em> Basic helix-loop-helix transcription factors JASMONATE-ASSOCIATED MYC2-LIKE1 (JAM1), JAM2, and JAM3 are negative regulators of jasmonate responses in arabidopsis. <em>Plant physiology</em> <strong>163</strong>, 291–304 (2013).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-song2013bhlh" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">6. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Song, S. <em>et al.</em> The bHLH subgroup IIId factors negatively regulate jasmonate-mediated plant defense and development. <em>PLoS genetics</em> <strong>9</strong>, e1003653 (2013).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-jung2020prion" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">7. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Jung, J.-H. <em>et al.</em> A prion-like domain in ELF3 functions as a thermosensor in arabidopsis. <em>Nature</em> <strong>585</strong>, 256–260 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-chee2022thermogenetics" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">8. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Chee, W. K. D., Yeoh, J. W., Dao, V. L. &amp; Poh, C. L. Thermogenetics: Applications come of age. <em>Biotechnology Advances</em> <strong>55</strong>, 107907 (2022).</div>
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>© 2024 Mauro Maver | This work is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{maver2024,
  author = {Maver, Mauro},
  publisher = {Omnia},
  title = {TWA1: A Novel Thermosensor Enhancing Plant Thermotolerance},
  volume = {1},
  number = {8},
  date = {2024-06-29},
  url = {https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VIII/},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.12582848},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {In this study, *Bohn et al.* identified
    THERMO-WITH-ABA-RESPONSE 1 as a novel thermosensor in *A.thaliana*.
    This sensor is crucial for thermotolerance and heat-stress response
    as it interacts with key transcription factors and co-repressors in
    a temperature-dependent mechanism. This discovery has the potential
    to significantly improve crop acclimation to global warming through
    biotechnological applications.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-maver2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<div class="">Maver, M. TWA1: a novel thermosensor enhancing
plant thermotolerance. <em>Omnia Focus</em> vol. 1 Preprint at <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12582848">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12582848</a>
(2024).</div>
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VIII/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VIII/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Plant-mediated soil effects on microbiota in plant-herbivore systems</title>
  <dc:creator>Mauro Maver</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VII/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="drop-cap">
<p>Soil has a significant impact on plants, profoundly influencing their microbiota. Studies have demonstrated that the influence of soil far exceeds that of other factors, such as plant genotype or the presence of insects<span class="citation" data-cites="tkacz2020influence malacrino2021soil"><sup>1,2</sup></span>. Indeed, soil microorganisms can colonise different parts of plants, like roots and leaves, affecting their microbiome or altering their physiological status. Overall, these soil-mediated effects are known as soil-driven effects. Similarly, the presence of herbivores can directly or indirectly influence plant microbiomes, known as herbivore-driven effects. However, few studies have explored the combined impact of soil- and herbivore-driven effects on the structure and diversity of microbial communities within plants.</p>
</div>
<p>Two possible mechanisms are hypothesised to explain the interactions between below- and above-ground microorganisms in a plant-herbivore system. The first mechanism involves direct mediation by the plant itself. For example, microorganisms can interact directly with the host plant or indirectly by improving the availability of nutritional resources. Alternatively, influence can occur via spillover, with direct transfer of microorganisms between above- and below-ground compartments, such as through insect frass or honeydew, or vice versa through splashes or droplets of water (e.g., rain or irrigation).</p>
<p>This study by <em>Malacrinò &amp; Bennett</em><span class="citation" data-cites="malacrino2024soil"><sup>3</sup></span> aims to clarify how microorganisms in a plant-herbivore system influence each other. They hypothesised that the plant itself primarily mediates the effects of soil and herbivores on plant microbiota. The experimental design included manipulating the soil composition (three different inocula), the presence/absence of herbivorous insects, and the effect of the presence/absence of soil cover.</p>
<p>The experiment was conducted on tomato plants (<em>Solanum lycopersicum</em> L.) grown in microcosms with three different soil microbial communities (agricultural field, marginal field, and prairie) selected for their distinct compositions. Half of the microcosms were covered with a neoprene disc at the soil level to separate “via plant” effects from “via spillover” effects, and half of them were exposed to the herbivore <em>Manduca sexta</em>. At the end of the experiment (7 weeks), microbial communities of soil, rhizosphere, root, leaf, and herbivores were analysed, along with plant and insect biomass.</p>
<p>The results of this study primarily show that soil inoculum has the most significant impact on the structure of bacterial communities in all plant compartments analysed, especially on root and herbivore microbiota. Additionally, it was interesting to note that changes induced by soil inoculum on herbivore microbiomes followed a linear gradient, with the greatest impact observed by agricultural soil and the least by prairie soil.</p>
<p>However, contrary to previous studies, it was observed that the soil-driven effect influences the leaf and herbivore microbiota regardless of the presence of the neoprene disc. These results thus support the hypothesis of a soil-driven effect “via plant.” This effect could be due to changes in plant metabolism and physiology, which in turn alter the diet of herbivores and their microbiome. Another possible explanation is the direct transfer of microorganisms from below ground to above ground via the xylem, as demonstrated by recent research<span class="citation" data-cites="wolfgang2023reciprocal"><sup>4</sup></span>. Furthermore, it was observed that soil microbial communities can negatively affect insect biomass. This factor is particularly interesting as it could lead to the development of more sustainable methods for controlling pathogens<span class="citation" data-cites="pineda2017steering french2021emerging"><sup>5,6</sup></span>.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the herbivore-driven effect can alter plant microbiome composition both directly and indirectly through changes in metabolism, plant physiology, and root exudates<span class="citation" data-cites="rolfe2019crying"><sup>7</sup></span>. Moreover, the data support the presence of microbial spillover between different plant compartments, although it is reduced when the soil is covered. This indicates that microbial spillover and plant-mediated changes in the below-ground microbiota could coexist in this specific system.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the study by <em>Malacrinò &amp; Bennett</em> demonstrates that the soil-driven effect on plant and herbivore microbial communities is mediated by the plant, not via spillover. At the same time, it was observed that the rhizosphere and root microbiota are influenced by microbial spillover from herbivores. These findings provide a clearer understanding of the interactions between soil, plants, and herbivores, with potential applications in improving agricultural practices by manipulating soil microbiota.</p>
<div style="text-align: center">
<iframe width="600" height="450" src="Omnia_focus_VII.pdf">
</iframe>
</div>
<div class="PDF">
<p>👉 <a href="Omnia_focus_VII.pdf" title="Here you can download the PDF version">Click here for the PDF</a> 👈</p>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p><strong>Original article</strong></p>
<p>Malacrinò A. &amp; Bennett A.E. (2024). Soil microbiota and herbivory drive the assembly of tomato plant-associated microbial communities through different mechanisms. <em>Communications Biology</em>, <strong>7</strong>: 564. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s42003-024-06259-6">doi.org/10.1038/s42003-024-06259-6)</a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>




<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-tkacz2020influence" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Tkacz, A., Bestion, E., Bo, Z., Hortala, M. &amp; Poole, P. S. Influence of plant fraction, soil, and plant species on microbiota: A multikingdom comparison. <em>MBio</em> <strong>11</strong>, 10–1128 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-malacrino2021soil" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Malacrinò, A., Karley, A. J., Schena, L. &amp; Bennett, A. E. Soil microbial diversity impacts plant microbiota more than herbivory. <em>Phytobiomes Journal</em> <strong>5</strong>, 408–417 (2021).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-malacrino2024soil" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Malacrinò, A. &amp; Bennett, A. E. Soil microbiota and herbivory drive the assembly of tomato plant-associated microbial communities through different mechanisms. <em>Communications Biology</em> <strong>7</strong>, 564 (2024).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-wolfgang2023reciprocal" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Wolfgang, A., Tack, A. J., Berg, G. &amp; Abdelfattah, A. Reciprocal influence of soil, phyllosphere, and aphid microbiomes. <em>Environmental Microbiome</em> <strong>18</strong>, 63 (2023).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-pineda2017steering" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">5. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Pineda, A., Kaplan, I. &amp; Bezemer, T. M. Steering soil microbiomes to suppress aboveground insect pests. <em>Trends in Plant Science</em> <strong>22</strong>, 770–778 (2017).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-french2021emerging" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">6. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">French, E., Kaplan, I., Iyer-Pascuzzi, A., Nakatsu, C. H. &amp; Enders, L. Emerging strategies for precision microbiome management in diverse agroecosystems. <em>Nature plants</em> <strong>7</strong>, 256–267 (2021).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-rolfe2019crying" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">7. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Rolfe, S. A., Griffiths, J. &amp; Ton, J. Crying out for help with root exudates: Adaptive mechanisms by which stressed plants assemble health-promoting soil microbiomes. <em>Current opinion in microbiology</em> <strong>49</strong>, 73–82 (2019).</div>
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>© 2024 Mauro Maver | This work is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{maver2024,
  author = {Maver, Mauro},
  publisher = {Omnia},
  title = {Plant-Mediated Soil Effects on Microbiota in Plant-Herbivore
    Systems},
  volume = {1},
  number = {7},
  date = {2024-06-21},
  url = {https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VII/},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.12188671},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {The study by *Malacrinò \&amp; Bennett* demonstrates that the
    soil-driven effects on plant and herbivore microbial communities are
    primarily mediated through the plant itself rather than through
    direct microorganism transfer. The results also highlight the impact
    of herbivores on the rhizosphere and root microbiota via microbial
    spillover. These findings offer insights into soil-plant-herbivore
    interactions with potential applications in sustainable agricultural
    practices.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-maver2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<div class="">Maver, M. Plant-mediated soil effects on
microbiota in plant-herbivore systems. <em>Omnia Focus</em> vol. 1
Preprint at <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12188671">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12188671</a>
(2024).</div>
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VII/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VII/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Modulation of lettuce responses to salinity by Graminaceae-derived protein hydrolysates</title>
  <dc:creator>Mauro Maver</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VI/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="drop-cap">
<p>The increasing salinisation of soil is a major challenge for modern agriculture, as it significantly and irreversibly reduces crop yields. Many studies are currently focusing on this problem, anticipating a continuous worsening mainly by climate change. Indeed, it is projected that by 2050, half of the world’s arable land will be unusable due to high salinity<span class="citation" data-cites="bartels2005drought"><sup>1</sup></span>.</p>
</div>
<p>Plants, particularly vegetables, are highly susceptible to salinity, which significantly affects their growth and productivity. Consequently, over the course of their evolution, plants have developed defence mechanisms and strategies, making them more adaptable and resilient under stressful conditions. Among the main defence responses include the modulation of phytohormones, the production of osmoprotectants, and antioxidant enzymes.</p>
<p>However, in cases of severe salinity, these endogenous responses activated by the plant may not be enough to support growth. In such conditions, external interventions, such as the application of plant biostimulants (PBs) derived from food waste or agricultural residues, could provide an effective and sustainable solution. Among PBs, protein hydrolysates (PHs) are particularly promising; composed of a mix of polypeptides, oligopeptides, and amino acids, their composition varies based on the protein source, thus determining their effects on the plant<span class="citation" data-cites="colla2015protein"><sup>2</sup></span>. A recent study demonstrated that PHs from <em>Graminaceae</em> induce diverse effects in lettuce (<em>Lactuca sativa</em> L.) under saline stress, although the contribution of individual fractions remains unclear<span class="citation" data-cites="el2023graminaceae"><sup>3</sup></span>. Lettuce, widely cultivated globally for its high nutritional value, is highly sensitive to salinity and is often used as a model plant in these studies.</p>
<p>In this context, <em>Monterisi et al</em>.<span class="citation" data-cites="monterisi2024integrated"><sup>4</sup></span> investigate the molecular effects of PHs derived from <em>Graminaceae</em> (P) and their light fraction F3 (&lt;1 kDa) on lettuce under saline stress conditions using a combined transcriptomic and metabolomic approach. In this experiment, lettuce plants were exposed to two levels of salinity, 0 mM and 30 mM NaCl. P and F3 treatments were applied via spray on a weekly basis, starting from the 10th day after transplanting (DAT); control plants received distilled water. Upon reaching commercial maturity (44 DAT), the plants were sampled and subsequently analysed using different approaches.</p>
<p>The results confirmed that the efficacy and mode of action of PHs strongly depend on the physiological status of the plant and the composition (fractionated and non-fractionated) of the biostimulants. In general, the authors demonstrated that both treatments, P and F3, significantly modulate the transcriptome and metabolomic profile of lettuce under saline stress, albeit through distinct mechanisms. For instance, P treatment resulted in the up-regulation of genes involved in biosynthesis and remodelling of the cell wall, cellulose hydrolysis, organic acid biosynthesis, osmoprotectant production, and antioxidants. On the other hand, F3 treatment showed a positive modulation in response to ethylene (via <em>ERF</em>) and genes involved in the <em>MAPK</em> signalling pathway, highlighting a regulation of salinity response mechanisms<span class="citation" data-cites="miransari2013salt"><sup>5</sup></span>.</p>
<p>Another interesting aspect concerns the P treatment. It was observed that P up-regulates 17 genes encoding different nucleosome components. These changes can influence the degree of chromatin condensation, making it more or less accessible to transcription factors. Abiotic stresses have already been shown to activate these epigenetic mechanisms in plants<span class="citation" data-cites="he2018abiotic"><sup>6</sup></span>, but this is the first time it has been observed for PHs in stressed plants.</p>
<p>From a multi-omics perspective, the integrated analysis of transcriptomics and metabolomics revealed that both P and F3 trigger a significant hormonal response under saline stress conditions. Among the main regulated phytohormones and respective pathways are ethylene, abscisic acid, auxin, and brassinosteroids. The latter, in particular, play an important role in plants in counteracting the negative effects of salinity by promoting cell division and elongation<span class="citation" data-cites="rattan2022involvement"><sup>7</sup></span>.</p>
<p>In the absence of saline stress, the data obtained are partially discordant with those present in the scientific literature. Indeed, both P and F3 exhibited a down-regulation of genes involved in different steps of the photosynthetic process. Although these data are consistent with the biochemical parameters recorded in the experiment, they contrast with previous studies that demonstrated the positive effects of PHs on the photosynthetic machinery.</p>
<p>In conclusion, <em>Monterisi et al</em>. demonstrate that PHs derived from <em>Graminaceae</em> and their molecular fractions can significantly modulate the molecular, biochemical, and physiological responses of lettuce under saline stress. Although P and F3 activate different mechanisms, both treatments provide benefits in counteracting severe salinity conditions. These findings underscore the importance of further investigating the bioactivity of the molecular components of biostimulants to fully maximise their potential in agricultural practices.</p>
<div style="text-align: center">
<iframe width="600" height="450" src="Omnia_focus_VI.pdf">
</iframe>
</div>
<div class="PDF">
<p>👉 <a href="Omnia_focus_VI.pdf" title="Here you can download the PDF version">Click here for the PDF</a> 👈</p>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p><strong>Original article</strong></p>
<p>Monterisi, S., Zhang, L., Garcia-Perez, P., Alzate Zuluaga, M.Y., Ciriello, M., El-Nakhel, C., Buffagni, V., Cardarelli, M., Colla, G., Rouphael, Y., Cesco, S., Lucini, L. &amp; Pii, Y. (2024). Integrated multi-omic approach reveals the effect of a Graminaceae-derived biostimulant and its lighter fraction on salt-stressed lettuce plants. <em>Scientific Reports</em>, <strong>14</strong>: 10710. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-61576-4">doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-61576-4</a></p>
<p><strong>List of abbreviations</strong></p>
<p><strong>PBs</strong>, plant biostimulants <strong>•</strong> <strong>PHs</strong>, protein hydrolysates <strong>•</strong> <strong>Da</strong>, Dalton <strong>•</strong> <strong>NaCl</strong>, sodium chloride <strong>•</strong> <strong>DAT</strong>, days after transplantation <strong>•</strong> <strong>ERFs</strong>, ethylene-responsive transcription factors <strong>•</strong> <strong>MAPK</strong>, mitogen-activated protein kinase.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>




<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-bartels2005drought" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Bartels, D. &amp; Sunkar, R. Drought and salt tolerance in plants. <em>Critical reviews in plant sciences</em> <strong>24</strong>, 23–58 (2005).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-colla2015protein" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Colla, G. <em>et al.</em> Protein hydrolysates as biostimulants in horticulture. <em>Scientia Horticulturae</em> <strong>196</strong>, 28–38 (2015).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-el2023graminaceae" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">El-Nakhel, C. <em>et al.</em> A graminaceae-derived protein hydrolysate and its fractions provide differential growth and modulate qualitative traits of lettuce grown under non-saline and mild salinity conditions. <em>Scientia Horticulturae</em> <strong>319</strong>, 112130 (2023).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-monterisi2024integrated" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Monterisi, S. <em>et al.</em> Integrated multi-omic approach reveals the effect of a graminaceae-derived biostimulant and its lighter fraction on salt-stressed lettuce plants. <em>Scientific Reports</em> <strong>14</strong>, 10710 (2024).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-miransari2013salt" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">5. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Miransari, M. <em>et al.</em> Salt stress and MAPK signaling in plants. <em>Salt Stress in Plants: Signalling, Omics and Adaptations</em> 157–173 (2013).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-he2018abiotic" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">6. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">He, M., He, C.-Q. &amp; Ding, N.-Z. Abiotic stresses: General defenses of land plants and chances for engineering multistress tolerance. <em>Frontiers in plant science</em> <strong>9</strong>, 1771 (2018).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-rattan2022involvement" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">7. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Rattan, A. <em>et al.</em> Involvement of brassinosteroids in plant response to salt stress. <em>Brassinosteroids in plant developmental biology and stress tolerance</em> 237–253 (2022).</div>
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>© 2024 Mauro Maver | This work is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{maver2024,
  author = {Maver, Mauro},
  publisher = {Omnia},
  title = {Modulation of Lettuce Responses to Salinity by
    {Graminaceae-derived} Protein Hydrolysates},
  volume = {1},
  number = {6},
  date = {2024-06-18},
  url = {https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VI/},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.11965373},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {This study by *Monterisi et al.* investigates the effects
    of protein hydrolysates from *Graminaceae* and their fractions on
    lettuce under saline stress. It reveals that both treatments
    modulate the plant’s transcriptome and metabolomic profile,
    enhancing its resilience to high salinity through distinct
    mechanisms. This study underscores the potential of protein
    hydrolysates to mitigate salinity stress in agriculture, promoting
    sustainable crop management.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-maver2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<div class="">Maver, M. Modulation of lettuce responses to
salinity by Graminaceae-derived protein hydrolysates. <em>Omnia
Focus</em> vol. 1 Preprint at <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11965373">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11965373</a>
(2024).</div>
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VI/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_VI/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Enhancing root-knot nematode invasion resistance in clover through root uptake of benzoxazinoids</title>
  <dc:creator>Mauro Maver</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_V/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="drop-cap">
<p>The evolution of plants has led to the development of complex defensive strategies based on metabolites, specifically secondary metabolites. Plants often co-evolved in biodiversity-rich environments, developing mechanisms to exploit metabolites released by other plants for their own defence. This phenomenon underpins co-cropping, where two crops grow in the same space, allowing chemical interaction between plants through metabolite release<span class="citation" data-cites="bertin2003role"><sup>1</sup></span>. In this context, one plant acts as the donor while the other as the target, with metabolites influencing growth, pathogen defence, and shaping rhizosphere communities.</p>
</div>
<p>Among these metabolites are benzoxazinoids (BXs), a class of compounds primarily found in <em>Poaceae</em>, which play crucial roles in the rhizosphere, such as soil pathogen defence and allelopathic effects<span class="citation" data-cites="hazrati2020root"><sup>2</sup></span>. An underexplored aspect is the uptake of BXs by plants that are naturally lacking and whether this can enhance their pathogen resistance. A relevant example is clover (<em>Trifolium</em> spp.), an important legume in many inter-cropping systems for its nitrogen-fixing ability. However, clover is also an excellent host for root-knot nematodes (<em>Meloidogyne</em> spp.)<span class="citation" data-cites="timper2006reproduction vestergaard2019trap"><sup>3,4</sup></span>.</p>
<p>In this context, <em>Hama et al.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="hama2024root"><sup>5</sup></span> investigated the uptake, transformation, and translocation of BXs, and how they influenced nematode resistance in white clover (<em>Trifolium repens</em> L.). Exposed to different BXs to facilitate absorption, clover plants were subsequently transferred to BXs-free soil. This soil was then inoculated with 2–7 day-old infective juveniles (J2 stage) of the root-knot nematode <em>Meloidogyne incognita</em>. Plants were sampled at 0, 3, 5.5, and 8 weeks post-transfer, analysing BXs concentrations and nematode invasion rates over time. The experiments were designed to separate the timing and location of BXs exposure from nematode infestation to prevent any direct effects of BXs on the nematodes.</p>
<p>The experiments demonstrated that clover could absorb and translocate the applied BXs to its leaves. Additionally, clover showed the ability to metabolise them, an example being the glycosylation of DIBOA into DIBOA-glc, a detoxification and storage mechanism common in BX-producing plants<span class="citation" data-cites="niemeyer2009hydroxamic"><sup>6</sup></span> but not previously observed in clover. However, by 5.5 weeks post-transfer, no BXs were detected, suggesting that without continuous exposure, BXs concentrations in clover diminish until undetectable.</p>
<p>A key aspect of the study was the effect of BXs on nematode invasion. The authors observed that exposure to BXs significantly reduced nematode invasion. At 3 weeks post-transfer, all tested BXs showed a significant reduction in nematode invasion compared to the control, with the greatest reduction observed for HBOA (-68%). However, the effect diminished over time, with a significant reduction in invasion rate at 5.5 weeks only for DIBOA and no difference at 8 weeks. This decline in nematode suppression mirrors the reduction in concentrations of BXs in the roots, as clover cannot naturally synthesise them.</p>
<p>This study is the first to show that the uptake of defence metabolites by other plant species can significantly improve pathogen resistance. Although nematode invasion in clover was notably reduced up to 5.5 weeks after the last BXs exposure, the effect diminished without continuous supply. This suggests that in a co-cropping context, the continuous release of BXs by producing plants like wheat or rye could maintain sufficient levels of these compounds in the soil, extending the protective effect in clover.</p>
<p><em>Hama et al.</em> study advances our understanding of plant interactions in co-cropping systems. It demonstrated that secondary metabolites such as BXs can be transferred from one plant to another, enhancing pathogen resistance. However, this effect is temporary and tied to the ongoing availability of BXs in the soil.</p>
<p>These findings suggest that intercropping with BX-producing plants could effectively improve pathogen resistance while reducing pesticide use. Further field studies are necessary to fully evaluate the long-term benefits and drawbacks of these interactions and develop optimal agricultural practices.</p>
<div style="text-align: center">
<iframe width="600" height="450" src="Omnia_focus_V.pdf">
</iframe>
</div>
<div class="PDF">
<p>👉 <a href="Omnia_focus_V.pdf" title="Here you can download the PDF version">Click here for the PDF</a> 👈</p>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p><strong>Original article</strong></p>
<p>Hama, J.R., Fomsgaard, I.S., Topalović, O., &amp; Vestergård, M. (2024). Root uptake of cereal benzoxazinoids grants resistance to root-knot nematode invasion in white clover. <em>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</em>, <strong>210</strong>: 108636. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2024.108636">doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2024.108636</a></p>
<p><strong>List of abbreviations</strong></p>
<p><strong>BXs</strong>, benzanoxinoids compunds (2,4-dihydroxy-1,4-benzoxazin-3-one, 2-hydroxy-1,4-benzoxazin-3-one, benzoxazolinone, and 6-methoxy- benzoxazolin-2-one) <strong>•</strong> <strong>DIBOA</strong>, 2,4-dihydroxy-1,4-benzoxazin-3-one <strong>•</strong> <strong>DIBOA-glc</strong>, 2-β-D-glucopyranosyloxy-4-hydroxy-1,4-benzoxazin-3-one <strong>•</strong> <strong>HBOA</strong>, 2-hydroxy-1,4-benzoxazin-3-one</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>




<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-bertin2003role" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Bertin, C., Yang, X. &amp; Weston, L. A. The role of root exudates and allelochemicals in the rhizosphere. <em>Plant and soil</em> <strong>256</strong>, 67–83 (2003).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-hazrati2020root" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Hazrati, H., Fomsgaard, I. S. &amp; Kudsk, P. Root-exuded benzoxazinoids: Uptake and translocation in neighboring plants. <em>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</em> <strong>68</strong>, 10609–10617 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-timper2006reproduction" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Timper, P., Davis, R. F. &amp; Tillman, P. G. Reproduction of meloidogyne incognita on winter cover crops used in cotton production. <em>Journal of nematology</em> <strong>38</strong>, 83 (2006).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-vestergaard2019trap" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Vestergård, M. Trap crops for meloidogyne hapla management and its integration with supplementary strategies. <em>Applied soil ecology</em> <strong>134</strong>, 105–110 (2019).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-hama2024root" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">5. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Hama, J. R., Fomsgaard, I. S., Topalović, O. &amp; Vestergård, M. Root uptake of cereal benzoxazinoids grants resistance to root-knot nematode invasion in white clover. <em>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</em> <strong>210</strong>, 108636 (2024).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-niemeyer2009hydroxamic" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">6. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Niemeyer, H. M. Hydroxamic acids derived from 2-hydroxy-2H-1,4-benzoxazin-3(4H)-one: Key defense chemicals of cereals. <em>Journal of agricultural and food chemistry</em> <strong>57</strong>, 1677–1696 (2009).</div>
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>© 2024 Mauro Maver | This work is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{maver2024,
  author = {Maver, Mauro},
  publisher = {Omnia},
  title = {Enhancing Root-Knot Nematode Invasion Resistance in Clover
    Through Root Uptake of Benzoxazinoids},
  volume = {1},
  number = {5},
  date = {2024-06-06},
  url = {https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_V/},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.11491221},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {This study by *Hama et al.* demonstrates that clover can
    absorb and metabolise benzoxazinoids from other plants,
    significantly enhancing its resistance to nematode invasion
    temporarily. The findings suggest that continuous benzoxazinoids
    release in co-cropping systems could sustain pathogen protection in
    non-benzoxazinoids-producing plants like clover.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-maver2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<div class="">Maver, M. Enhancing root-knot nematode invasion
resistance in clover through root uptake of benzoxazinoids. <em>Omnia
Focus</em> vol. 1 Preprint at <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11491221">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11491221</a>
(2024).</div>
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_V/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_V/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Enhanced photosynthesis in rice with far-red light supplement: unveiling dual roles beyond shade avoidance</title>
  <dc:creator>Mauro Maver</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_IV/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="drop-cap">
<p>Light represents the primary source of energy for plants. Plants have developed elaborate strategies to maximise light exposure throughout their long evolution. This need is particularly crucial in environments with high vegetation density, where competition for light can be intense.</p>
</div>
<p>In photosynthesis, the light spectrum between 400-700 nm is fundamental, while light between 700-800 nm, known as far-red (FR), contributes to photosynthesis only under specific conditions (e.g., Emerson effect)<span class="citation" data-cites="emerson1958quantum"><sup>1</sup></span>. FR light is mainly known for its role as a signal indicating the presence of nearby vegetation. Nearby plants reflect FR light while absorbing red light, thus decreasing the Red:FR (R:FR) ratio. This reduction signals the proximity of other plants, triggering the shade avoidance syndrome (SAS). SAS induces changes in plant architecture, such as internode elongation, at the expense of forming new leaves and branches. Rice (<em>Oryza sativa</em>), one of the most important crops, is known for its sensitivity to high vegetation density and low light, although its response to SAS and to the R:FR ratio is still poorly studied.</p>
<p>A study by <em>Huber et al.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="huber2024far"><sup>2</sup></span> examined the effect of supplemental FR light on architecture, growth, and the photosynthetic process in seven rice varieties. The plants were grown in a greenhouse under control conditions with white light (WL with R:FR 2.0), while the treatment involved supplemental FR light (WL + FR, R:FR 0.2). Analysis of the rice architecture revealed that plants exposed to FR exhibited an increase in leaves and tillers compared to those grown only in WL. This effect varied among the different rice varieties studied. However, no significant differences were observed in terms of height and internode length, indicating a weak SAS response and a promotion of vegetative growth.</p>
<p>Following transcriptome analysis in 5-day-old seedlings, only a small number of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) from FR were common among all rice varieties. Specifically, only one gene (<em>LOC_Os09g27750</em>), which encodes an ethylene‐forming enzyme, was identified in all the varieties analysed. Subsequent Gene Ontology (GO) enrichment analysis showed that all genes regulated by FR, although limited in number, were primarily involved in photosynthetic processes and localised at the chloroplast level. Overall, the impact of FR on gene regulation was limited to specific physiological processes.</p>
<p>Despite the weak SAS response in rice, a key aspect of the study was the effect of FR light on biomass accumulation and photosynthesis. The results showed that plants exposed to FR light had a higher rate of leaf formation, increased total leaf area, and more tillers, leading to a significant increase in root and shoot biomass. This effect was further confirmed with FR pulse treatments at the end of the light cycle (15 min WL + EoD FR) to further trigger SAS. In this case, a reduction in tillers and leaves was observed, suggesting that WL + FR can indeed promote growth and development in rice.</p>
<p>To better understand the role of FR in promoting biomass accumulation and plant development, the authors focused on investigating the effects of FR light on photosynthesis. They found that supplemental FR light did not significantly alter stomatal density or chlorophyll content. However, carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) fixation was significantly increased only in plants exposed to WL + FR, with some varieties showing almost double the fixation compared to the control. Additionally, no effects on stomatal conductance were observed, suggesting that FR can increase photosynthesis without causing greater water loss through transpiration, contrary to blue and red photons<span class="citation" data-cites="chen2012systems matthews2020role"><sup>3,4</sup></span>.</p>
<p>This study by <em>Huber et al.</em> demonstrated that FR light not only acts as a shade/proximity signal but also as an energy source for photosynthesis and biomass accumulation, consistent with other studies<span class="citation" data-cites="park2017far zhen2020far"><sup>5,6</sup></span>. WL + FR significantly increased growth and photosynthetic processes in rice without activating a noticeable SAS response. This suggests that rice may rely on other light signals (such as blue or red light) or chemical signals (e.g., volatile organic compounds) to sense the density of surrounding vegetation. Furthermore, the weak SAS response in rice may have been overshadowed by the strong promotion provided by the FR supplement.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the interaction between FR and the photosynthetic photon flux density (PPFD) in photosynthesis needs further investigation, especially to understand how FR can compensate for a reduction in PPFD, particularly in the lower canopy zones<span class="citation" data-cites="huber2021light"><sup>7</sup></span>. These results are particularly relevant for optimising light in greenhouse and vertical farming systems, where controlling light quality and quantity is crucial for maximising plant growth and productivity.</p>
<div style="text-align: center">
<iframe width="600" height="450" src="Omnia_focus_IV.pdf">
</iframe>
</div>
<div class="PDF">
<p>👉 <a href="Omnia_focus_IV.pdf" title="Here you can download the PDF version">Click here for the PDF</a> 👈</p>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p><strong>Original article</strong></p>
<p>Huber, M., de Boer, H.J., Romanowski, A., van Veen, H., Buti, S., Kahlon, P.S. et al.&nbsp;(2024). Far-red light enrichment affects gene expression and architecture as well as growth and photosynthesis in rice. <em>Plant, Cell &amp; Environment</em> 1–18 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/pce.14909">doi.org/10.1111/pce.14909</a></p>
<p><strong>List of abbreviations</strong></p>
<p><strong>nm</strong>, nanometre <strong>•</strong> <strong>SAS</strong>, shade avoidance syndrome <strong>•</strong> <strong>R:FR</strong>, red to far‐red light ratio <strong>•</strong> <strong>WL</strong>, white light <strong>•</strong> <strong>WL + FR</strong>, white light with supplemental far‐red light <strong>•</strong> <strong>WL + EoD FR</strong>, end of day far‐red light (EoD FR) <strong>•</strong> <strong>PPFD</strong>, photosynthetic photon flux density.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>




<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-emerson1958quantum" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Emerson, R. The quantum yield of photosynthesis. <em>Annual Review of Plant Physiology</em> <strong>9</strong>, 1–24 (1958).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-huber2024far" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Huber, M. <em>et al.</em> Far-red light enrichment affects gene expression and architecture as well as growth and photosynthesis in rice. <em>Plant, Cell &amp; Environment</em> 1–18 (2024).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-chen2012systems" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Chen, Z.-H. <em>et al.</em> Systems dynamic modeling of the stomatal guard cell predicts emergent behaviors in transport, signaling, and volume control. <em>Plant Physiology</em> <strong>159</strong>, 1235–1251 (2012).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-matthews2020role" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Matthews, J. S., Vialet-Chabrand, S. &amp; Lawson, T. Role of blue and red light in stomatal dynamic behaviour. <em>Journal of Experimental Botany</em> <strong>71</strong>, 2253–2269 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-park2017far" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">5. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Park, Y. &amp; Runkle, E. S. Far-red radiation promotes growth of seedlings by increasing leaf expansion and whole-plant net assimilation. <em>Environmental and Experimental Botany</em> <strong>136</strong>, 41–49 (2017).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-zhen2020far" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">6. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Zhen, S. &amp; Bugbee, B. Far-red photons have equivalent efficiency to traditional photosynthetic photons: Implications for redefining photosynthetically active radiation. <em>Plant, Cell &amp; Environment</em> <strong>43</strong>, 1259–1272 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-huber2021light" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">7. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Huber, M., Nieuwendijk, N. M., Pantazopoulou, C. K. &amp; Pierik, R. Light signalling shapes plant–plant interactions in dense canopies. <em>Plant, Cell &amp; Environment</em> <strong>44</strong>, 1014–1029 (2021).</div>
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>© 2024 Mauro Maver | This work is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{maver2024,
  author = {Maver, Mauro},
  publisher = {Omnia},
  title = {Enhanced Photosynthesis in Rice with Far-Red Light
    Supplement: Unveiling Dual Roles Beyond Shade Avoidance},
  volume = {1},
  number = {4},
  date = {2024-05-23},
  url = {https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_IV/},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.11216924},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {This study by *Huber et al.* demonstrates that
    supplemental far-red light significantly enhances growth and
    photosynthetic efficiency in rice without triggering a strong shade
    avoidance syndrome response. This suggests that far-red light serves
    a dual role as an energy source and a proximity signal. These
    findings are crucial for optimising light management in greenhouse
    and vertical farming to maximise plant productivity.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-maver2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<div class="">Maver, M. Enhanced photosynthesis in rice with
far-red light supplement: unveiling dual roles beyond shade avoidance.
<em>Omnia Focus</em> vol. 1 Preprint at <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11216924">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11216924</a>
(2024).</div>
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_IV/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_IV/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>13C dynamics in forest rhizosphere microbial communities under drought and rewetting</title>
  <dc:creator>Mauro Maver</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_III/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="drop-cap">
<p>Global climate change is causing a series of severe weather events like prolonged droughts followed by heavy rainfalls, posing a growing threat to forest ecosystems worldwide. Understanding the crucial link between plants and rhizosphere microbial communities during drought periods is fundamental, as it significantly influences soil community structure and functionalities, with carbon (C) transport and release by plants into the rhizosphere playing a key role.</p>
</div>
<p>In this context, <em>Gao et al.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="gao2024drought"><sup>1</sup></span> investigated the impact of drought and soil rewetting on forest rhizosphere microbial communities. The study was conducted on 4-year-old European beech (<em>Fagus sylvatica</em>) forests under artificial conditions and approximately 120-year-old Scots pine (<em>Pinus sylvestris</em>) forests under natural growth conditions. The authors applied a combination of isotopic labelling techniques with <sup>13</sup>C and molecular analyses to trace the flow of C initially absorbed by plants, subsequently released into the soil, and then incorporated by microbial communities. <sup>13</sup>C labelling was performed at the leaf level during drought and two weeks after rewetting. These data were compared with those obtained from the control treatment, consisting of constantly irrigated plants. This approach allowed them to explore in detail the mechanisms regulating rhizosphere microbial community dynamics in response to drought and rewetting events in two different forests.</p>
<p>During drought, a significant reduction in <sup>13</sup>C uptake was observed in both forest types at both plant and soil microbial community levels. This phenomenon has been previously observed in grasslands<span class="citation" data-cites="fuchslueger2016drought karlowsky2018land"><sup>2,3</sup></span>; however, this experiment showed a significant decrease in symbiotic fungi, particularly ectomycorrhizal fungi (ECM) (biomarker 18:2ω6,9). This decline could compromise water and nutrient availability for plants, thereby affecting their growth and ability to withstand strong water stress, further exacerbating their stress status. Among the less negatively affected microorganisms were gram-positive bacteria, which have a thicker peptidoglycan membrane and are therefore more drought resistant.</p>
<p>Moreover, at the cellular level, the authors observed a shift in the functional use of <sup>13</sup>C absorbed by microbial communities. Indeed, during drought, there was a significant decrease in <sup>13</sup>C incorporated into phospholipid fatty acids (PLFAs) compared to microbial cytoplasm (CFE-microbial biomass). This would indicate a greater priority towards energy conservation, osmoregulation, and storage processes, at the expense of cell growth. PLFAs are the main components of cell membranes, and their reduced presence would indicate a modulation in the use of fresh root exudates released by plants into survival and adaptation strategies rather than development<span class="citation" data-cites="mason2023intracellular"><sup>4</sup></span>.</p>
<p>Upon restoration of optimal soil moisture conditions, both in beech and pine, microbial communities demonstrated remarkable resilience and recovery from the severe drought experienced. One of the main explanations for this strong resilience lies in the rapid restoration of tree C allocation in the rhizosphere at the end of the drought. One of the most interesting aspects observed was a greater incorporation of <sup>13</sup>C into microbes, compared to the control, despite normal leaf <sup>13</sup>C uptake values. This implies a preferential transfer and incorporation towards rhizosphere communities, strengthening their role in plant functioning and maintaining forest ecosystem health<span class="citation" data-cites="joseph2020rhizosphere gao2021drought"><sup>5,6</sup></span>.</p>
<p>In addition, this study highlighted differences between beech and pine forests in the response of microbial communities to drought and subsequent rewetting. Beech forests showed more pronounced effects, with greater sensitivity to drought and a more pronounced response to rewetting. Conversely, in pine, the effect of rewetting had a lesser impact, perhaps due to the long-term adaptation of microbial communities to repeated natural drought events. Overall, these results may have been influenced by both the experimental conditions applied (more drastic and artificial in the case of beech) and the different sizes and biomass of the plants. The examined pine plants had more biomass (greater height) and consequently greater C storage. This would allow them to have greater buffering capacity in case of C content, transport, and release changes compared to beech, for example, under adverse growth conditions.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the study conducted by <em>Gao et al.</em> provides important insights into the complex interactions between plants and soil microbial communities during drought and soil moisture restoration periods. The results obtained also offer valuable tools for understanding the mechanisms underlying the resilience of forest ecosystems, which are increasingly subject to rapid climate change.</p>
<div style="text-align: center">
<iframe width="600" height="450" src="Omnia_focus_III.pdf">
</iframe>
</div>
<div class="PDF">
<p>👉 <a href="Omnia_focus_III.pdf" title="Here you can download the PDF version">Click here for the PDF</a> 👈</p>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p><strong>Original article</strong></p>
<p>Gao, D., Luster, J., Zürcher, A., Arend, M., Bai, E., Gessler, A., Rigling, A., Schaub, M., Hartmann, M., Werner, R.A., Joseph, J., Poll, C. &amp; Hagedorn, F. (2024). Drought resistance and resilience of rhizosphere communities in forest soils from the cellular to ecosystem scale – insights from 13C pulse labeling. <em>New Phytologist</em> <strong>242</strong>: 960-974 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19612">doi.org/10.1111/nph.19612</a></p>
<p><strong>List of abbreviations</strong></p>
<p><strong>CFE-microbial biomass</strong>, chloroform fumigation extraction- microbial biomass</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>




<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-gao2024drought" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Gao, D. <em>et al.</em> Drought resistance and resilience of rhizosphere communities in forest soils from the cellular to ecosystem scale–insights from 13C pulse labeling. <em>New Phytologist</em> <strong>242</strong>, 960–974 (2024).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-fuchslueger2016drought" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Fuchslueger, L. <em>et al.</em> Drought history affects grassland plant and microbial carbon turnover during and after a subsequent drought event. <em>Journal of Ecology</em> <strong>104</strong>, 1453–1465 (2016).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-karlowsky2018land" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Karlowsky, S. <em>et al.</em> Land use in mountain grasslands alters drought response and recovery of carbon allocation and plant-microbial interactions. <em>Journal of Ecology</em> <strong>106</strong>, 1230–1243 (2018).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-mason2023intracellular" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Mason-Jones, K., Breidenbach, A., Dyckmans, J., Banfield, C. C. &amp; Dippold, M. A. Intracellular carbon storage by microorganisms is an overlooked pathway of biomass growth. <em>Nature Communications</em> <strong>14</strong>, 2240 (2023).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-joseph2020rhizosphere" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">5. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Joseph, J. <em>et al.</em> Rhizosphere activity in an old-growth forest reacts rapidly to changes in soil moisture and shapes whole-tree carbon allocation. <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em> <strong>117</strong>, 24885–24892 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-gao2021drought" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">6. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Gao, D. <em>et al.</em> Drought alters the carbon footprint of trees in soils—tracking the spatio-temporal fate of 13C-labelled assimilates in the soil of an old-growth pine forest. <em>Global Change Biology</em> <strong>27</strong>, 2491–2506 (2021).</div>
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>© 2024 Mauro Maver | This work is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{maver2024,
  author = {Maver, Mauro},
  publisher = {Omnia},
  title = {13C Dynamics in Forest Rhizosphere Microbial Communities
    Under Drought and Rewetting},
  volume = {1},
  number = {3},
  date = {2024-05-13},
  url = {https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_III/},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.11148076},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {This study by *Gao et al.* investigates the impact of
    drought and soil rewetting on forest rhizosphere microbial
    communities, tracing the dynamics of carbon-13
    (\textsuperscript{13}C) in European beech and Scots pine forests.
    Findings reveal significant shifts in \textsuperscript{13}C uptake
    and microbial community resilience, shedding light on ecosystem
    responses to climate change-induced stressors.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-maver2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<div class="">Maver, M. 13C dynamics in forest rhizosphere
microbial communities under drought and rewetting. <em>Omnia Focus</em>
vol. 1 Preprint at <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11148076">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11148076</a>
(2024).</div>
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_III/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_III/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Redefining tinnitus: a complex neurological disorder and its genetic roots</title>
  <dc:creator>Sara Gomez-Cabellos</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_II/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="drop-cap">
<p>When was the last time you heard nothing, just silence? What a strange question to ask, you might be thinking. My answer might differ from yours, when I was 16. I suffer from tinnitus, continuous “<em>ringing noises</em>” in both of my ears, and my loyal companion for more than 20 years now.</p>
</div>
<p>The definition of tinnitus is precisely the phantom sensation of “<em>ringing in the ears</em>” or, in other words, the perception of noise in the absence of external acoustic stimulation. Despite being experienced by more than 15 % of the world’s population, it does not have a cure. The only solutions for those who suffer from it are limited to reducing their psychological distress or masking the symptoms by external sound sources. Still, there are no targeted treatments for the pathophysiological mechanisms<span class="citation" data-cites="mcferran2019there"><sup>1</sup></span>.</p>
<p>Tinnitus can be continuous, pulsatile, or episodic, affecting one or both ears. It can last only a few moments, months, years, or a lifetime. Severe tinnitus is a debilitating condition experienced by 1% of the population, and it has been discovered to have a significant heritability<span class="citation" data-cites="trpchevska2020sex maas2017genetic"><sup>2,3</sup></span>.</p>
<p>Environmental factors were thought to be the main drivers of tinnitus for decades, but the widespread availability of sequencing data from distinct cohorts has opened new research possibilities<span class="citation" data-cites="vona2022road"><sup>4</sup></span>. The first study that defined tinnitus as a complex disorder in which genes and environmental factors interact was conducted by <em>Clifford et al.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="clifford2020novel"><sup>5</sup></span>, performing a genome-wide association study (GWAS) using large datasets from self-reported tinnitus. The following year, <em>Wells et al.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="wells2021genome"><sup>6</sup></span>, with a case-control GWAS, identified <em>RCOR1</em> (<em>REST COREPRESSOR 1</em> ) as the gene with the highest significance in a sub-group of patients with the most severe form of tinnitus. Nevertheless, even though both analyses of GWAS used UK Biobank participants, there was little overlap in the strongest associations between both studies, possibly because of the significant heterogeneity in tinnitus phenotype<span class="citation" data-cites="vona2022road"><sup>4</sup></span>.</p>
<p>GWAS allows the identification of significant common variants with small effect sizes that confer susceptibility to tinnitus. However, <em>Amanat et al.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="amanat2021burden"><sup>7</sup></span> used a different approach to identify the enrichment of rare pathogenic variants and target candidate genes. This strategy consisted of selecting individuals with extreme clinical attributes, toxic effects, or extreme responses to treatments, <em>i.e.</em>, extreme phenotype<span class="citation" data-cites="amanat2020systematic"><sup>8</sup></span>, to narrow the phenotypic heterogeneity that tinnitus manifests.</p>
<p><em>Amanat et al.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="amanat2021burden"><sup>7</sup></span> aimed to identify rare variants in synaptic genes by exome sequencing of Spanish patients with Ménière’s disease and an extreme tinnitus phenotype, performing a gene burden analysis (GBA). The disease of Ménière is a rare ear disorder characterized by intense episodes of vertigo, tinnitus, and hearing loss<span class="citation" data-cites="perez2020current"><sup>9</sup></span>. After years of the disease, patients consider tinnitus the most debilitating symptom<span class="citation" data-cites="ueberfuhr2017tinnitus herraiz2006tinnitus"><sup>10,11</sup></span>.</p>
<p>Their research uncovered a burden of rare missense and structural variants in several synaptic genes. Three candidate genes, <em>ANK2</em> (<em>ANKYRIN-2</em> ), <em>TSC2</em> (<em>TSC COMPLEX SUBUNIT 2</em> ), and <em>AKAP9</em> (<em>A-KINASE ANCHOR PROTEIN 9</em> ), were replicated in a Swedish cohort of patients with severe tinnitus. Moreover, to determine if the association of these genes was specific to severe tinnitus, they performed a GBA using an independent cohort of patients with generalized genetic epilepsy who did not have tinnitus. Some neurological disorders, such as epilepsy, could also share some common genetic background with tinnitus. None of the genes showed significant enrichment of missense variants, confirming the tinnitus-specificity of the candidate genes.</p>
<p>Gene ontology and gene-set enrichment analysis uncovered the involvement of membrane trafficking and cytoskeletal protein binding in neurons. <em>ANK2</em>, <em>TSC2</em>, and <em>AKAP9</em> are associated with axonal branching and neuron connectivity in the brain, and their expression in spiral ganglion neurons was confirmed. Furthermore, <em>ANK2</em> and <em>TSC2</em> showed significant co-expression in limbic brain regions.</p>
<p>This study presents several limitations, such as a lack of representation of the whole phenotype of Ménière’s disease using the extreme phenotype strategy or the possibility that other neural pathways unrelated to synapses are also implicated in tinnitus. Nevertheless, it provides a first reference point in understanding the molecular players in severe tinnitus, and it could be a significant step forward in its future treatment.</p>
<div style="text-align: center">
<iframe width="600" height="450" src="Omnia_focus_II.pdf">
</iframe>
</div>
<div class="PDF">
<p>👉 <a href="Omnia_focus_II.pdf" title="Here you can download the PDF version">Click here for the PDF</a> 👈</p>
</div>
<!-- ::: {.callout-note appearance="minimal"} -->
<!-- **Original article** -->
<!-- Huang, P-K., Schmitt, J. & Runcie, D.E. (2024). Exploring the molecular regulation of vernalization-induced flowering synchrony in Arabidopsis. *New Phytologist* **242**: 947-959 [doi.org/10.111/nph.19680](https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19680) -->
<!-- **List of abbreviations** -->
<!-- **SD**, short days, 8h:16h (day:night cycle) **•** **MD**, medium days, 12h:12h **•** **LD**, long days, 16h:8h **•** ***FLM***, *FLOWERING LOCUS M* **•** ***TSF***, *TWIN SISTER OF FT* **•** ***MAF3***, *MADS AFFECTING FLOWERING 3* **•** ***SOC1***, *SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CO 1* **•** ***AGL19***, *AGAMOUS-LIKE 19*. -->
<!-- ::: -->




<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-mcferran2019there" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">McFerran, D. J., Stockdale, D., Holme, R., Large, C. H. &amp; Baguley, D. M. Why is there no cure for tinnitus? <em>Frontiers in neuroscience</em> <strong>13</strong>, 466176 (2019).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-trpchevska2020sex" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Trpchevska, N. <em>et al.</em> Sex-dependent aggregation of tinnitus in swedish families. <em>Journal of Clinical Medicine</em> <strong>9</strong>, 3812 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-maas2017genetic" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Maas, I. L. <em>et al.</em> Genetic susceptibility to bilateral tinnitus in a swedish twin cohort. <em>Genetics in Medicine</em> <strong>19</strong>, 1007–1012 (2017).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-vona2022road" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Vona, B. The road traveled and journey ahead for the genetics and genomics of tinnitus. <em>Molecular Diagnosis &amp; Therapy</em> <strong>26</strong>, 129–136 (2022).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-clifford2020novel" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">5. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Clifford, R. E., Maihofer, A. X., Stein, M. B., Ryan, A. F. &amp; Nievergelt, C. M. Novel risk loci in tinnitus and causal inference with neuropsychiatric disorders among adults of european ancestry. <em>JAMA Otolaryngology–Head &amp; Neck Surgery</em> <strong>146</strong>, 1015–1025 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-wells2021genome" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">6. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Wells, H. R., Abidin, F. N. Z., Freidin, M. B., Williams, F. M. &amp; Dawson, S. J. Genome-wide association study suggests that variation at the RCOR1 locus is associated with tinnitus in UK biobank. <em>Scientific Reports</em> <strong>11</strong>, 6470 (2021).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-amanat2021burden" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">7. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Amanat, S. <em>et al.</em> Burden of rare variants in synaptic genes in patients with severe tinnitus: An exome based extreme phenotype study. <em>EBioMedicine</em> <strong>66</strong>, (2021).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-amanat2020systematic" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">8. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Amanat, S., Requena, T. &amp; Lopez-Escamez, J. A. A systematic review of extreme phenotype strategies to search for rare variants in genetic studies of complex disorders. <em>Genes</em> <strong>11</strong>, 987 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-perez2020current" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">9. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Perez-Carpena, P. &amp; Lopez-Escamez, J. A. Current understanding and clinical management of meniere’s disease: A systematic review. in <em>Seminars in neurology</em> vol. 40 138–150 (Thieme Medical Publishers, 2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-ueberfuhr2017tinnitus" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">10. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Ueberfuhr, M. A., Wiegrebe, L., Krause, E., Gürkov, R. &amp; Drexl, M. Tinnitus in normal-hearing participants after exposure to intense low-frequency sound and in m<span>é</span>ni<span>è</span>re’s disease patients. <em>Frontiers in neurology</em> <strong>7</strong>, 219513 (2017).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-herraiz2006tinnitus" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">11. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Herraiz, C., Tapia, M. &amp; Plaza, G. Tinnitus and meniere’s disease: Characteristics and prognosis in a tinnitus clinic sample. <em>European Archives of Oto-Rhino-Laryngology and Head &amp; Neck</em> <strong>263</strong>, 504–509 (2006).</div>
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>© 2024 Sara Gomez-Cabellos | This work is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{gomez-cabellos2024,
  author = {Gomez-Cabellos, Sara},
  publisher = {Omnia},
  title = {Redefining Tinnitus: A Complex Neurological Disorder and Its
    Genetic Roots},
  volume = {1},
  number = {2},
  date = {2024-05-02},
  url = {https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_II/},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.10955449},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {What is tinnitus exactly? A shift in the conception of
    tinnitus from being just a symptom of an underlying condition to
    being recognized as a neurological disorder redefines its
    long-established dogma definition.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-gomez-cabellos2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<div class="">Gomez-Cabellos, S. Redefining tinnitus: a
complex neurological disorder and its genetic roots. <em>Omnia
Focus</em> vol. 1 Preprint at <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10955449">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10955449</a>
(2024).</div>
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_II/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_II/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Floral synchrony: the role of FLOWERING LOCUS T in the leaf-specific vernalisation response in Arabidopsis</title>
  <dc:creator>Mauro Maver</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_I/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<!-- This study by Huang et al. explores the intricate relationship between vernalisation, leaf-specific responses, and flowering synchrony in Arabidopsis thaliana. They uncover how leaf development during vernalisation impacts the expression of key flowering genes, suggesting a complex interplay between leaf-based processes and meristem regulation in determining flowering timing. -->
<div class="drop-cap">
<p>The synchronisation of flowering is important for plants as it helps them to reproduce efficiently and adapt to their environment. One key mechanism regulating this synchrony is vernalisation, where plants are induced to flower after being exposed to low temperatures for a long time. However, it is not fully understood how vernalisation helps plants belonging to heterogenous populations to synchronize their flowering.</p>
</div>
<!-- <p class="drop-cap"></p> -->
<!-- <p><span class="first-letter">O</span>nce upon a time in a faraway land...<p> -->
<!-- <font style="font-family: Bell MT, sans-serif; font-size:55pt; font-style:regular; width: .85em; line-height: 53px; float: left; color: #7D3C98; border: solid #D5C5EC; padding-top: 5px; padding-bottom: 5px; padding-right: 5px; padding-left: 5px; margin-right: 5px; margin-bottom: -5px;">L</font>a fisiología -->
<p>The present study conducted by <em>Huang et al.</em><span class="citation" data-cites="huang2024exploring"><sup>1</sup></span> aims to investigate how the <em>FLOWERING LOCUS T</em> (<em>FT</em> ) gene affects the regulation of floral synchrony in <em>Arabidopsis thaliana</em>, focusing on its impact in response to vernalisation. Through a series of experiments, the researchers examined the role of genes involved in the flowering process and evaluated the importance of what they call “<em>leaf-specific vernalisation response</em>” in its regulation. The study hypothesised that leaves may have a “cold memory” that differs depending on their developmental stage at the onset of vernalisation.</p>
<p>The experiments were conducted on the Col-<em>FRI</em> genotype of <em>A. thaliana</em>, which was obtained by introgressing the <em>FRIGIDA</em> locus (<em>FRI</em> ) into Col, thus making its flowering vernalisation-dependent. In the first experiment, Col-<em>FRI</em> seeds were germinated sequentially (cohorts on different days preceding vernalisation induction), grown under controlled light and temperature conditions (SD, 8 weeks of vernalisation at 4°C and LD until flowering), and their flowering time was recorded. It was observed that the Col-<em>FRI</em> genotype showed synchronised flowering (positive synchronisation index (SI)<span class="citation" data-cites="miryeganeh2020synchronization"><sup>2</sup></span>) among different groups despite germination occurring at distinct times. In contrast, Col showed asynchronous flowering among the various groups, exhibiting a negative SI.</p>
<p>Replicating prior experiments investigating the <em>FLOWERING LOCUS C</em> (<em>FLC</em> ) gene<span class="citation" data-cites="finnegan2007vernalization"><sup>3</sup></span>, a repressor of <em>FT</em>, the authors analysed the expression levels of the latter in relation to the leaf-specific vernalisation response. Again, using sequential germination experiments of Col-<em>FRI</em>, it emerged that <em>FT</em> expression was not strictly correlated with the number of leaves present at the time of flowering but rather with a specific number of leaves which developed after vernalisation induction. This confirms the presence of an intricate flowering regulation mechanism based on leaf number and their developmental stage at the onset of low temperatures.</p>
<p>To minimise the possible effect of photoperiod on <em>FT</em> expression level analyses, the authors applied SD photoperiod both before and after vernalisation. This allowed the confirmation of the <em>FLC</em> expression values reported in the literature<span class="citation" data-cites="finnegan2007vernalization"><sup>3</sup></span> (elevated in the absence and before vernalisation) while simultaneously observing uniform <em>FT</em> expression values in leaves developed during and after vernalisation. These data indicate that <em>FLC</em> and <em>FT</em> expression levels are not positively (or negatively) correlated. Furthermore, this suggests that the relationship between leaf development and vernalisation is more evident and marked for <em>FT</em> compared to <em>FLC</em>.</p>
<p>In addition to <em>FT</em> and <em>FLC</em>, the authors evaluated the expression levels of five other genes involved in flowering pathways: <em>FLM</em>, <em>TSF</em>, <em>MAF3</em>, <em>SOC1</em>, and <em>AGL19</em>. Leaf-specific vernalisation response was also observed for these genes, although with different and gene-specific expression patterns. Among all the genes analysed, only <em>FLC</em> and <em>SOC1</em> showed diametrically opposite expression patterns. For the remaining genes, a strong effect of leaf-specific vernalisation response was observed. In fact, higher expression levels were found in leaves developed during and after vernalisation.</p>
<p>Finally, the researchers assessed the impact of leaf-specific vernalisation response compared to other regulatory processes, such as those deriving from the shoot apical meristem (SAM). In a last experiment of Col-<em>FRI</em> sequential germination, they established a MD photoperiod following the eight weeks of vernalisation and monitored <em>FT</em> levels until flowering. Data showed an <em>FT</em> expression pattern similar to that observed in the presence of post-vernalisation LD conditions, but with an intensity almost five times lower. Contrary to the low <em>FT</em> levels, the delay in flowering was slight and not significantly prolonged. This suggests that other non-leaf-dependent signals may play a significant role in regulating flowering in response to vernalisation.</p>
<p>The study conducted by <em>Huang et al.</em> represents one of the first attempts to establish a clearer relationship between flowering pathways and flowering synchrony in response to vernalisation. In Arabidopsis, the authors observed a correlation between leaf-specific vernalisation response and floral synchrony, although this does not represent the only factor at play. Other non-leaf-based signals, such as those generated by the shoot apical meristem, could play an important role as well. Another key factor emerging from this study was the lack of correlation between <em>FLC</em> and <em>FT</em> expression levels, despite the former acting as a strong repressor of <em>FT</em>.</p>
<p>Overall, the research conducted in Arabidopsis by <em>Huang et al.</em> contributes to a better understanding of leaf-level interaction between vernalisation and floral synchrony, paving the way for further investigations in this field.</p>
<div style="text-align: center">
<iframe width="600" height="450" src="Omnia_focus_I.pdf">
</iframe>
</div>
<div class="PDF">
<p>👉 <a href="Omnia_focus_I.pdf" title="Here you can download the PDF version">Click here for the PDF</a> 👈</p>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p><strong>Original article</strong></p>
<p>Huang, P-K., Schmitt, J. &amp; Runcie, D.E. (2024). Exploring the molecular regulation of vernalization-induced flowering synchrony in Arabidopsis. <em>New Phytologist</em> <strong>242</strong>: 947-959 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.19680">doi.org/10.111/nph.19680</a></p>
<p><strong>List of abbreviations</strong></p>
<p><strong>SD</strong>, short days, 8h:16h (day:night cycle) <strong>•</strong> <strong>MD</strong>, medium days, 12h:12h <strong>•</strong> <strong>LD</strong>, long days, 16h:8h <strong>•</strong> <strong><em>FLM</em></strong>, <em>FLOWERING LOCUS M</em> <strong>•</strong> <strong><em>TSF</em></strong>, <em>TWIN SISTER OF FT</em> <strong>•</strong> <strong><em>MAF3</em></strong>, <em>MADS AFFECTING FLOWERING 3</em> <strong>•</strong> <strong><em>SOC1</em></strong>, <em>SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CO 1</em> <strong>•</strong> <strong><em>AGL19</em></strong>, <em>AGAMOUS-LIKE 19</em>.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>




<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a><div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-huang2024exploring" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Huang, P.-K., Schmitt, J. &amp; Runcie, D. E. Exploring the molecular regulation of vernalization-induced flowering synchrony in arabidopsis. <em>New Phytologist</em> <strong>242</strong>, 947–959 (2024).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-miryeganeh2020synchronization" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Miryeganeh, M. Synchronization of senescence and desynchronization of flowering in arabidopsis thaliana. <em>AoB Plants</em> <strong>12</strong>, plaa018 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-finnegan2007vernalization" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Finnegan, E. J. &amp; Dennis, E. S. Vernalization-induced trimethylation of histone H3 lysine 27 at FLC is not maintained in mitotically quiescent cells. <em>Current biology</em> <strong>17</strong>, 1978–1983 (2007).</div>
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>© 2024 Mauro Maver | This work is licensed under CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{maver2024,
  author = {Maver, Mauro},
  publisher = {Omnia},
  title = {Floral Synchrony: The Role of {FLOWERING} {LOCUS} {T} in the
    Leaf-Specific Vernalisation Response in {Arabidopsis}},
  volume = {1},
  number = {1},
  date = {2024-04-17},
  url = {https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_I/},
  doi = {10.5281/zenodo.10955449},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {This study by *Huang et al.* explores the intricate
    relationship between vernalisation, leaf-specific responses, and
    flowering synchrony in *Arabidopsis thaliana*. They uncover how leaf
    development during vernalisation impacts the expression of key
    flowering genes, suggesting a complex interplay between leaf-based
    processes and meristem regulation in determining flowering timing.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-maver2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
<div class="">Maver, M. Floral synchrony: the role of
FLOWERING LOCUS T in the leaf-specific vernalisation response in
Arabidopsis. <em>Omnia Focus</em> vol. 1 Preprint at <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10955449">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10955449</a>
(2024).</div>
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_I/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.mauromaver.eu/posts/posts_omnia/omnia_focus_I/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
